welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where equal hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
check-ins feel calm and I have a desire
to say something more interesting than
calm
welcome to the stoah my name is Peter
Lindbergh on the Stewart of the stoah
and the Stowe as a place for us to
cohere and dialogue about what matters
most the nice edge and today we have my
buddy
Benjamin Boyce it's gonna be a good one
he's the one waving right now with the
interesting background so how that is
gonna work Raven is going to have a
conversation with Ben and then if you
have a question just throw it in the
chat box if you want rayvin tweeter on
your behalf
just indicate that in the chat box this
will go on youtube so if you don't want
to be on YouTube you know get Raven to
read it
that being said Raven will introduce Ben
and we'll start from there
hi everybody so Benjamin Boyce is the
host of the YouTube channel and podcast
the voice of reason this channel was
critical and documenting the Evergreen
meltdown that happened almost three
years to the day ago and sent him on a
trajectory of inquiry that continues to
this day his podcast covers a lot of
hot-button issues about sex and gender
and transitioning and D transitioning so
things that are like very critical
topics to be discussing right now but he
does he does it in such a way that I
really respect and it really relates to
some of the issues of memetic mediation
that we've been talking about here at
the stoah like how do we have
conversations across ideological bounds
so I'm really excited to to have
Benjamin here to kind of discuss and
reflect on his project of his podcast so
Ben welcome to the Stella you're on mute
sorry yeah thanks for having me
great I just want to like you know it's
the three-year anniversary of of the
meltdown and I thought that maybe we
would just if you had any thoughts or
reflections looking back after these
last three years well yeah plenty but
how brief of an overview do I need to
give is everybody aware of the protests
what happened three years ago basically
there was a series of protests at the
Evergreen State College the Evergreen
State College is a very small liberal
arts college in Olympia Washington and
after the election of Donald Trump a
series of protests erupted on campus
that got more and more brazen that
culminated in well it began it
culminated in a week-long series of
protests beginning with the protests of
Brett Weinstein who's the brother of
Eric Weinstein he's an evolutionary
biologist and Brett had been I guess
arguing against certain certain methods
that the college was implementing to
make the college life
around anti-racism and he had some
qualms with the way in which they were
going about implementing equity and he
was you know he argued with other
faculty and staff about that and those
emails got into the hands of the student
journal the Cooper pointer and all the
student newspaper and then got into the
hands of the protesters now the
protesters weren't really intending to
protest brett weinstein he was just one
example that they wanted to make of a
quote-unquote racist faculty and
unfortunately for them they accused him
of many things that were demonstrably
untrue about his racist his racism or
whatever and then the the protesters
went on to take over the administration
building to kind of basically take
people hostage to roam the campus with
baseball bats to assault people who were
writing in chalk that they wanted class
and and they uploaded and live-streamed
all of their protests onto the internet
and it shows some of the most egregious
behavior that you could probably come
across in the 2010s kind of the social
justice activism era that i think we're
kind of in a new phase of though some
things are happening on twitter that
that seemed to want to reboot that stuff
but um anyway so the campus kind of
became the laughingstock of the internet
for a few weeks well for a few months
and became kind of a harbinger for
progressivism gone toxic and that
sparked a whole lot or it was the kind
of like the lightning rod for a lot of
discussions around what it means to be
anti-racist what it means to be
progressive and what it means to be
conservative in these issues now while
the internet was roundly mocking the
protesters for acting the way that they
did I had been a student there and I had
been kind of on camera for a lot of the
lectures and seminars and orientations
and workshops that the college was
putting on that basically I've argued
since the that point that the college
was setting up the students
to act this way the college was
programming students to become radicals
and to not be very nuanced with the ways
in which they wanted to effect
progressivism and also not really giving
them the tools to combat criticism when
it eventually came in fact the college
itself guarded and coddled the
protesters before during and after the
protests and to the state of the college
and still not made amends and they're
actually apologized or done any thorough
review of what actually happened anyway
so I had been on camera for a lot of
those workshops and then I went through
because it's a state institution I got
that footage the public records requests
and I began to go through the emails and
the videos and present it to the public
to try to get a full 360 degree
exploration of the causes of the
behavior of the students and then the
outcomes too and really try to map out
as thoroughly as possible everything
that happened and the ideas that were
germinating and driving and propelling
all of those events so it's been three
years and I'm about finished with a 24
episode documentary that lays out
everything that I have except for the
emails there's just too many emails to
read but all the footage and trying to
give a complete story to that and I'm
almost done with that and I guess
there's a lot of lessons to take from
that but um maybe I should ask you let
you ask another question because I just
rambled for 10 minutes tonight you know
that's really helpful framing I think
for everybody yeah I mean I was also on
campus at the time and I can really
attest to the tension that there was and
being between worlds of just like
knowing that I had all these friends who
were just absolutely compelled by the
narrative that of the protests and were
calling Brett a racist and rallying
around these things and and living with
anarchist I mean it was a really crazy
and difficult time to be at Evergreen to
be at the center of all of this so I
guess I'm wondering about this
contemporary situation that you're
speaking
you kind of arise a new a new wave of
maybe political activity is there any
lessons that we can take from from what
happened at Evergreen that may apply to
what you see happening today well I
think that what you guys are doing here
I don't I don't recall the the words
that use mimetic masochism or something
like that I mediation mediation all
right I wasn't that fat I spending a
great deal of time really investigating
the Evergreen State College you know the
whole thing I needed to branch out
because I kind of ended up with a
YouTube channel and it kind of turned
into a very you know humble sort of
source of income and it was a business
and I was finally creating content and
interacting with an audience which is
something that I really wanted to do so
I needed to branch out and one of the
things I ended up doing was interviews
because I wanted to bring to YouTube
some content that I thought would be
unique and that would be desirable kind
of following kind of following the
interest in loosely following the
interest of Jordan Jordan Peterson
because Jordan Pederson was bringing an
academic content to the youtubes that
was already there but he he was kind of
making it really popular he was turning
a lot of people on to it and in various
levels of awareness and and interaction
and discourse so I began to interview
you know academics first but then I kind
of realized that oh well I I'm good at
listening and asking the right questions
and and I can get the I can get my
interviewee to really open up and get
into a different level of discourse and
eventually I started to interview
individuals around and this is going to
get back to your question I began to
interview individuals that were trans or
who had transitioned their their sex or
their gender or who had begun that
process and then reverted from that
process and I began and this is very
this is a very ideal well this is a very
direct manifestation
of the evergreen way of learning is that
you choose a topic and you really get
into it and you really speak with people
who are different from you and and you
really try to just provide as a broad
range of data into a topic and really
get deep into it and as I progressed in
investigating gender sexuality and
transition I I for whatever reason I
started to contact people in various
different relationships to that topic
feminists who had been I had been pretty
strongly criticizing a certain brand of
kind of contemporary op-eds ism I was
pretty critical of that sort of feminism
but then I I'm like well if I want to go
further with understanding gender I need
to speak with women who have been
thinking about gender and thinking about
it in a different way than me and and so
I began to speak with a broad range of
feminists and and researchers and and
sexuality I got to speak with some of
the top researchers in the field and and
then a lot of young people too and to
get back to your question what I what
what kind of initiated my interest in
the transition gender topic was because
I saw through what happened at Wilfrid
Laurier University in the fall of 2017
where this TA Lindsay Sheppard got you
know kind of GU logged a bit by her
professors for showing a problematic
Peterson clip but I saw a lot of trans
activists start to grandstand and use
that as a way to shut down discourse and
to become very authoritarian under the
trans umbrella and I saw with at
Evergreen that you have these activists
who are taking the identity at the
Evergreen State College of blackness or
of being black and then elect themselves
as the representative of that group and
and then because they're operating on a
group level and not an individual level
excuse any sort of behavior that's not
civil or not really take any
responsibility for their behavior as
individuals because they're acting
on behalf of some sort of large
structural historical continuum that
that excuses because of their it's
excuses all their means in the pursuit
of that ends and I wanted to rescue not
trans individuals but rescued the trans
discourse from the activists I wanted to
to basically erode the activists
stranglehold on the conversation
by speaking to people who weren't
activists but who were trans or D trans
or researchers into this and and engage
with that topic in such a way that the
the the contentiousness wasn't involved
in my form of discourse the my form of
discourse was a lot more patient a lot
more long-form and a lot more human and
grounded in individuality grounded in
the a personal narrative and so that you
can see especially with the with
feminists especially the academic
feminists who are acting or who are
thinking through things on an
ideological level you could see by
engaging with them in an interview that
all of their ideas were grounded in
their experience and so instead of
having an argumentative discussion up
here we're having a human discussion
that then branches off and grounds and
has a circular dialogue with the
ecosystem of lived experience of being a
human being interacting through an
identity and through a culture so I
think that that is my my basic tact to
take the wind out of the sails sales of
of activism and and I the racial
tensions in America are very exhausting
and there were too much for me and even
to this day it's it's a really fraught
conversation there's a lot of trauma and
suffering and and a lot of like lower
kind of very strong currents that that
are very difficult to deal with and so I
was kind of trying to take a break from
that while still up still trying to
wrestle with activism by going to a
gender topic which is
not as fraud as the racial conversation
that's going on we from your experience
interviewing and meeting people what
would you say are like the tensions in
in the trans community but inside of
like from from the individual
perspective rather than kind of the
activist portrayal of what the issues
are but rather from the perspective of
people in their lived experience the the
questions kind of self-defeating because
we're either talking about the
individual or we're talking about the
community and and the way that I've gone
about it and I should say that I'm by no
means an expert in in gender and
sexuality and transition at all at all
and and my my stance towards that topic
is one of inquiry I do have some
opinions about activism and I use and I
mock the activist portion of the LGBTQ
stuff I taco I on Twitter I engage in
that low-level discourse because I'm
fighting against a certain way of
framing that but when you get out of
that conversation and you go into okay
what is it like to be a trans person or
what is it like to experience gender
dysphoria what is it like to be in such
distress that it is a valid form of
remedy of that distress to subject your
body to some very intense grueling and
permanent changes and even tie yourself
to a medical you know like a lifestyle
that's afforded by a medical industry
also there's there's there's a big
contingent and this is very
controversial there's a studies suggest
and this is controversial that there is
a very strong large wave of young people
that are being being convinced by their
their culture online or by internal
sorts of understanding that they are in
the wrong
and they are before the age of adulthood
attaching themselves to the medical
industry and they are furthermore
through that medical industry through
the fields of psychology through the
fields of activism they're being
championed and and rushed down this path
that is that I don't really think a
young person really understands what
gender is I don't even think most of us
understand what gender is I think that
the whole conversation of what gender is
has gone through such a rapid radical
reboot that we don't really even know
what we're talking about anymore so
there there's this contingent within the
trans community called their
derogatorily called
true scum or because they believe that
in order to transition in order to
justify your transition you need to have
gender dysphoria you need to have a very
strong discordance between your you know
your perception and your physical
reality and that transition is rooted in
that medical kind of black box of the
brain matching up with the body and
there's a lot of theories to that
there's this other contingent that's
basically controlling the conversation
right now that is acting on these
theories about gender being a social
construct that that says that you don't
need to transition to be trans you don't
need to have gender dysphoria to start
to take testosterone if you're a female
or start to take estrogen if you're a
male you just you it's kind of it's so
it's a weird phenomenon that seems to be
pre transhumanism it's where human
beings are starting to use our
technology to modify our bodies and our
beings to to match up with some sort of
self-discovery it's it's this taking of
the ancient process of the hero's
journey let's say or a spiritual process
there's a lot of there's a lot of
similarities I see between ancient
spiritual traditions and transition as
it is enacted and spoken about within
that gender the transgender can be
as opposed to the transsexual community
that's going on that that I I have
opinions on but what I'm trying to do is
give people access to thinking about it
in a more nuanced unless less urgent
activist way of motive of engaging with
a topic can you speak a little bit more
into the connection to the spiritual
practices and the difference between the
transsexual community and the in the
trans community yeah okay again I just
need it because it's gonna go on on
YouTube so I'm by no means an expert
this is just me investigating this kind
of on the level of a hobby for a year
and a half and I'm just looking at it
through a cultural kind of narrative
about a month ago
give or take a article appeared in an
Australian newspaper written by a mother
about her female child and her female
child began to go on a walk that
instigates menopause at an early age
this pre not fully sexually developed
female was going on these hormones that
were instigating menopause and the
mother was speaking about it in this
really weird celebrate' it was weird to
me she was speaking about it in a very
celebratory way that her son had self
discovered and that the pain of this
menopause was this connection with their
true self in their true life and it made
me think about there's still tribes and
stuff that there's a lot of ancient
traditions where the the youth in order
to become a member of the clan in order
to become an adult is subjected to some
sort of rigor is subjected to some sort
of you know public shaming or you get
whipped or you get put into a box and
you go through this death or you
confront this pain and there was a lot
of that unconscious mapping of this
process of of maturation
that was this is this is contentious but
it was there was this mutilation
involved that was representing for the
mother the child becoming their true
self as though and there was this talk
about authenticity there's a lot of
weird little triggers for me in the
conversation that that make it seem very
kind of late-stage commercialism kind of
you you're choosing to be authentic
you're gonna come to us as the doctors
we're gonna make you understand who you
really are and I think that that is very
dangerous when we reduce our process of
taking self ownership of discovering
ourselves of becoming more and more
expansive and and instead of I think
about it I I think that the best way to
go about that from my life is to become
a master of something to pursue
literature let's say or or to be really
good at my craft that's how i unlock who
i really am is to produce something
outside of me or I do something in the
world this is this weird kind of end of
individualistic I become something and I
take the world and I shape myself into
the image of what I believe I am at that
moment as though what you believe you
are is a static construct as though you
can say I Know Who I am that that is
really dangerous because it's it's it's
not humble at all and and it's filled
with hubris and furthermore you're
enacting it with medications and with
scalpels right and there's tribes that
to this day they do ritual scarring or
with regards to you know I guess
genitals the young males in certain
cultures they're there their foreskins
taken like there's there there have been
instances of surgical or alteration that
that make a statement about belonging to
a clan but this is about belonging to
yourself and that ties into the really
interesting currents within
within these online communities and
tumblr and in reddit in these LGBTQ
communities where there's these there's
this kind of there's aspects in certain
portions of these communities that lines
up very much to cult-like behaviors
where you're where you are loved bombed
and you're praised for going down this
thing end and then you're stifled from
asking questions if you start asking
questions in these communities you begin
to be policed in various ways and I
again I have to be very careful
constantly and say I'm not speaking
about LGBTQ people themselves I'm
talking about certain manifestations
within the culture that is that is using
this identity to just recreate very old
tradition very old patterns of behavior
but but not really being aware that it
ties back to these ancient things like
like back to back to the garden of
knowledge or whatever great thank you
and Peter I see you have a question
would you like to ask it yeah so it's a
question of a culture war profiteering
and cancel culture there's some people
that there's an impression at least
among some tribes that the people in the
intellectual dart where I've been of
those Jason sort of responses that
they're profiteering off the culture war
and I think there's some charitable
interpretations and on charitable
interpretations there I don't get the
sense that you're doing at all and so
I'm kind of hearing as a reaction to
social justice voices and also canceled
culture have you got any run-ins with
the foot soldiers of canceled culture
based off of the subject matter that
you've been talking about yeah those are
great big questions the grift
the grifter are you guys I guess you can
nod yes or no you guys involved on
Twitter this is we're on Twitter there's
this perpetual accusation of being
grifter that goes around in it and it
affects all quadrants of the political
compass where you just it's kind of the
out-group deriding somebody who's acting
in bad faith about a topic and there's
certain there's certain people where you
wonder if they are actually grifting and
then there's certain people were it's
really evident and sorry to say this but
in my estimation Candis Owens is very
good at saying things that are very
inflammatory that get her a lot of play
but that don't really work out and
actually forwarding understanding it's
more like making a concrescence around a
tribe or like reinforcing her status as
the mouthpiece for an ideology um I
think that it might be it reminds me in
a sense if you it reminds me of a sense
back when I was growing up in the 90s
late 90s and I was like I was in my
early 20s and I was an artiste
and I was really afraid of being called
pretentious I was very sensitive to
being called pretentious like I'm a
pretender to making beautiful things and
and I think that there is a certain
level of self inventory and being
authentic and and if you do receive
money for the product that you're giving
off that transaction is actually
necessary to produce things and to
produce things that are in-depth and to
produce things that have power so tying
your ideology or your ideological
motivation to money doesn't necessarily
invalidate the authenticity of what
you're trying to do it for my own self
I've tried to not chase numbers not
chase being big not really there's
there's an ego that's there that's fine
to be there it's it keeps me abreast of
what other people are doing am i doing
good enough in my relevant and my am I
playing the game
in the right way but my orientation is
towards a kind of a longer run game like
I want to I want to enforce a form of
dialogue that will last longer than the
culture war with regards to how big and
wavy it is I do play that game I do play
the kind of the the witty you know
shitposting I do that and I don't not do
that I do do that but if you look just
one step down I have a number of
different levels of discourse that I'm
gay and gained that I am engaging on
that that if people if people see a
viral tweet they'll they'll eventually
see that I'm actually leading them down
a path to a deeper level of discourse so
I'm trying to operate on different
levels of discourse and I think a
grifter in the bad faith since only ever
act in acts a certain form of very
shallow short-sighted discourse and then
makes a lot of you know makes a living
or a name for themselves up there and
doesn't really do any of that deep
diving stuff cancellation cultures
really interesting I'm gonna get
cancelled again but I was I was
cancelled a couple months ago and it was
by the feminists because I had started
speaking with feminists and I got along
with some of them some public feminists
Megan Murphy being one who she got
cancelled literally by Twitter in 2018
but because I was following that line of
inquiry I started to do a lot of just
platforming very strong feminist voices
and platforming that side of the
transgender debate because there's this
contention between the transgender Asst
and the gender critical feminists and
that that's a whole mappy thing and i
was trying to map out the gender
critical side and i could do better with
being fair with the transgender side but
they're really weird when they get get
into there when they start actually
exposing what they think it is really
weird stuff so because i was shining
light on the gender criticals I got a
lot of gender critical followers and I
said something about me being rational
with regards to my intimate
relationships and how the females that I
am intimate with help me with my
emotions and I help them with just
thinking rationally and I shouldn't have
said that I was kind of high on I think
it was whiskey and and one of those pain
pills oxycodone because I had a injury
or something so I shouldn't have said
that but that led to this huge pile on
that was ironically really irrational
the way that they interacted with me but
you know but but over the last six
months I've had this run-in where a
tweet or a statement will get a certain
level of exposure and then exposed me to
a kind of ravenous anti movement against
me and and recalibrating myself under
that pressure it's been really a growing
experience to me because when when I'm
not joking around I'm doing these
interviews and what I'm doing the
interviews I'm I'm working on a very
emotionally sensitive level like I'm
being very quiet and still in myself and
I'm allowing through that to get some
very intimate to capture some very
intimate pictures or aspects of the
people that I'm interviewing but that
that being vulnerable also is not a good
idea when you're receiving hate because
I'll really internalize that so it's
been really interesting to learn how to
shield myself from from certain sorts of
negative energies that come at me while
still being able to accept or to to to
receive the criticism and then to
process that and to me being better at
what I'm doing so for I I will be
cancelled again I'm trying to be and I'm
trying to be cancel retardant in a way
by interacting in good faith with a
number of people in a number
of these different groups so that if I
get cancelled by let's say the gender
critical feminists I will have some very
big names in the gender critical
community that will speak to me about
that or will have my back right so so
I'm trying to interact with people on an
individual level so that it's really
hard to make me what happened to brent
Weinstein was that he was turned into a
cartoon of himself I'm trying to resist
that cartoon efficacious of me in the
light of being canceled by being too
complex and too weird or too
multifaceted to be collapsed into that
one little box that can be then you know
pilloried or forever stained is that one
little thing that's good yeah so the
first part it was like modeling good
conversation for the long game and then
and then this one is just being human
for the long game yeah like it Lisa's
like 7080 years very much I'm giving
Walter would you like to followup with
your question like where are these
coming from the chat oh they're in the
chat oh yeah sure can you hear me yeah
okay
I was just wondering there's this
argument that some of this less evidence
based kind of weaker arguments that you
see within some of these activist
spheres are coming because there's sort
of leftover institutional framework from
perhaps the gay rights movement where
there it's have you have you heard the
term the iron law of institutions
basically a framework that says if an
institution has been around for some
time
eventually the actors within the
institution become more focused on
advancing the institution rather than
the causes that the institution it was
originally put in place for so some one
argument might be that a lot of the
these wonderful old charities and
nonprofits from the AIDS crisis are
still around
and in order to retain donations they
have to look for new things to grow and
it's sort of like what sort of a
Milwaukee problem as Scott Alexander and
all that sort of a self creating thing
that and then I wonder if that's maybe
where some of the less good arguments
might be coming from just because it's
not coming from the heart it's coming
from this big institutional monster yeah
I think this is really fascinating to me
on a sociological philosophical
psychological level on studying
activists and studying what you're
saying there and one thing that I've
noticed is that we have a lot of these
institutions like the New York Times or
let's say the ACLU that are going down
this path of betraying some of the
foundational principles of civil liberty
let's say where the ACLU is championing
some sort of Title X some sort of
certain modes of legalese that actually
limit speech that actually harm you know
preponderance of evidence harm these
ancient these really old bedrock values
that we have and the New York time does
that too on an ideological level or
let's say with within the boundaries of
the gender critical gender transgender
discourse you have Meg major magazines
like science that's just called science
that's how science e it is it's just
called science they're like now saying
that sex doesn't exist that is some sort
of construct of the mind or something
like that and what I notice is that you
have these institutions that are now
held by people who are expending the
authority so the institution has over
time gained all this authority by being
authoritative by acting in a behavior
that's trustworthy and now you have
these individuals that are expending
that in order to make certain gains with
regards to let's say the charity I think
it's a UK charity called Stonewall which
was founded on gay rights and now over
since gay marriage came through
you see them switch and all this money
goes directly into transit the
transgender riots and you see them now
deleting tweets where they're saying
that homosexuality is a is a
biologically based attraction to the
same sex whereas now their official
stance is that you can be a lesbian if
you identify as a female like they're
now going over to this weird hyper it's
just unreal why somebody would think
that or why these categories would be
swapped about that why why we have
allowed people to decouple the
biological sex of what it is to be a
woman and all the processes that that a
female goes through and her development
mentally physically all that stuff plus
all of the processes that a woman a
female goes through in her cultural
development all that stuff which is a
huge bundle of complexity and very
strong very excruciating and and
wonderful you know the processes that
are pre ancient and and being able to
take that category and then just make it
not mean anything by by just handing it
over to whoever wants to identify into
that you can just elect yourself into
that and and there's a number of
different ways to react to that I react
to that because I think that it's it's
slandering something that for me I
conceived of as sacred like the female
is sacred it's it's something that's
off-limits that I need to compose myself
towards respect towards because that is
what caused me to have life and that's
what causes more life to exist so just
on the very foundational I'm not talking
individual women I'm just talking on the
the concept of female is a very
important category for me because
protecting that category ensures that I
and that which follows from I persists
through time it's a very important
category insofar as we are biological
entities
but that is just eroded now for the sake
of what and and one more kind of
off-topic thought or kind of tangential
thought is that the activist isn't there
to be right they're not there to pursue
with the truth they're there to get
their way and and you can go through any
sort of activist I guess group and you
can see rampant hypocrisy where there's
one statement and another statement that
are made with the same amount of
conviction and the same amount of power
and the same amount of urgency but if
you put them together they don't make
sense
they don't make sense as a as a coherent
whole as a system of thought but they
only ever make sense in forwarding the
activists will and once you see that
truth it goes all the way back to pre
Stowe at I'm sorry it goes back to you
know Plato and and Socrates and and you
had Socrates going down one court one
frame of discourse that's aiming towards
I guess the good or the true and then
you have the Sophists that are going
down another course of discourse about
gaining power of persuading the populace
to act in a certain way and both of
those frames of discourse I think need
to come into harmony because you have to
have some sort of action from your
thoughts you have to follow your
thoughts and and maybe maybe
Christianity tried to in certain forms
tried to harmonize those two things in
that discourse around faith and works
like you need to have the right faith
which is orthodoxy and then the right
practice orthopraxy and trying to bring
those two in a land alignment but but it
has to check out and and you'll see that
they'll switch discourse in order to
keep you off center in order to maintain
their control there's a lot of judo
going on and that happens in any given
discourse when the volume and the
temperature is is turned up and so what
I think that we need to do is constantly
kind of turning the temperature down or
providing a lot of cool headed behavior
where that level high radioactive level
of very
reactive activists kind of discourse
really doesn't make any sense because
everybody's kind of calm and like
talking through things rationally but
when you have these institutions that
are forwarding this agenda who further
will have all this money going on behind
it
furthermore you have these psychologists
and these doctors that are acting in a
way that I don't think is proper towards
young children and putting them on a
path of sterility and of confusion and
of sorry to say in certain cases I think
you could argue mutilation for the rest
of their lives according to a Dogma that
is really hot right now but in ten years
might not be as hot anymore might not be
the thing to want to become when you're
a teenager that that is a terrible
tragedy and that's something that I kind
of get it up aren't up in arms about
thank you maybe would you like to ask
your question thank you um something
that I heard you say in sort of your
introduction was that a big part of what
concerns you is about this sort of
medicalization of our reader standing of
gender that's clearly been triggered at
this like kind of cultural moment I see
like this really concerning thing where
it was not very long ago that the
wellness industry was offering
conversion therapy to what they saw as
like confused homosexuals who were
suffering a mental illness and now the
same community who who had to live
through that which is just horrible it
is is giving so much trust to the same
industry to help them carry out
something that is you know potentially
as transformative without questioning
whether it's as harmful and and I also
hear you speak to the idea that
sexuality and physicality and gender
have been spiritual concepts for as long
as they've been biological concepts and
the wellness industry is trying to sort
of fill both gaps right now in ways they
you don't sound like you think are
necessarily always
appropriate and I would I would really
like to hear more about your concerns
about the medicalization and the lack of
like spiritual support to counter it or
or question it am i ok there's one of my
regular guests is a licensed
professional counselor I believe she
works specifically with gender
questioning youth or young people who
are really wrestling with the concepts
of gender and her name is Sasha I odd
and some of my best content is is in our
discussions about this topic because she
one of the things that she really
stresses is that youth today especially
females but males as well because of
let's say internet because of the
internet because of the the disembodied
sexuality that's performed upon the
Internet they are coming into an
understanding of sex that is through the
head and not through the body so there's
this whole generation who discovers sex
through videos and through through
sounds and lights and devices these
little these these things that are made
out of metal and plastic and stuff and
what does that do to one sexuality what
does that do to let's say a female who
says oh that is what I'm supposed to be
I'm supposed to be treated that way that
is what sex is or and not even that but
but there's this whole disembodied
aspect of oh I should be pansexual I
should be homosexual like what what is
my sexuality and and any talk I've
spoken with a number of young women
probably in their 20s more or less who
who go through that who talked about
like the last 10 years of their
development and and not even really
desiring other people like there's no
real eros there's no real I I love that
or are like I'm turned on by that that
immediacy that physicality is gone and
it's all replaced by this abstracted
form of sex where it's not human it's
not even it's not it's not even
biological anymore it's this it's this
game the shadowy game so you see you see
that level of disassociation happening
on such a profoundly personal activity
of sexuality and desire like that which
that which pre-internet is something
that you discovered you know like like
out on the town you know or like you
kind of fumbled your way through it and
and and that fumbling to know like well
like with the post me too era and and me
too I don't separate that from the
rampant disregard and harassment and
oppression of females based on their sex
by men based on their sexuality
I want to abstract that from that into
that cultural artifact of the
conversation around consent when I was
at the Evergreen State College one of
the orientations that you go through is
about is about consent and and it's like
in order for me to have a spontaneous
sexual interaction I need to like bring
out this five page manual on all these
different line items that we need to
sign and and verbalize and then every
five minutes I need to ask permission
are you okay and all that all that quiet
meditation between one individual
discovering another individual is MPAs
colonized by the brain is colonized by
the mind is colonies by legalese is
colonized by all these repercussions and
not to say that consent isn't absolutely
necessary in order for respectful adult
sexual intercourse to occur but there is
a way that's gone about it that's so
clinical and has a lot of what you're
talking about about the wellness
industry a lot of this kind of
dissociated from reality kind of
clinical like separation and and where
does that leave emotional development
how do you develop a human full human
understanding of yourself and other
people as human beings if it's all
mediated through on one level
pornography on another another level of
this consent culture and then this
not to write anybody who's on tender but
like that that really that
commodification of of interpersonal and
interactivity it's all it's an exchange
of pleasure it's an exchange of pleasure
and I think that we're we're watching I
think we forget that we're in the middle
of a cultural experiment where the 60s
came through and and introduced a lot of
liberation so-called and we are now kind
of living through successive generations
of more and more Liberatore behavior and
then how that how that is managed how do
we bring order into that chaos is it's a
big question and and how do we do that
how do we make communities how do we how
do we facilitate young men and women to
go through a profound amount of
development and understand the
consequences of sex as as another human
being which i think is a really big
point that we overlook when we talk
about sexuality that's how we all got
here you know like so maybe that maybe
that should be reason for us to respect
it a little bit you know and and to
leave it leave some amount of religious
kind of awe in the face of that when we
intellectualize them thank you thank you
maybe for that question I want to do a
call out see if there's any more
questions before I before we kind of
wrap up here anybody else
Peter I think tell if these are
questions or statements in a lot of
these yeah I know
economists might have had a question or
no I think there's a lot of expression
about the difficulty of talking about
this stuff that's happening in the chat
and and also the difficulty of being
gentlemen gender non-conforming in this
context and kind of talking about all of
the complexity of these issues and I
don't know if you have anything you'd
like to say about about just speaking on
these things and well I think that I I
peppered my conversation with enough
apology or you know cancellation
retardants
of kind of contextualizing I can only
speak from my experience I do have I do
have very I do have a place in my heart
for old ideas that are thoroughly
outmoded and and and I I justify that
because by way of saying that I'm
dealing with gender on a spectrum of
different levels of the concept of what
a male and a female is and I think that
manures in a very rudimentary
mythological level and then it goes all
the way up into a modern level where you
you interact with somebody who's gender
non-conforming you interact with
somebody who is female but very
masculine or who's who's male but very
feminine and and seeing all of those
ideas play out on a human being seeing
all those ideas allowing for those
concepts to interact on an individual
level
not as enforcement's of a stereotype but
as a sort of expression of these very
deep patterns of biology and psychology
that are emerging through us as
individuals and every individual is a
mixture of all these different concepts
and and to be able to to interact with
the stereotype and the archetype and not
a lot not and to kind of section that
off to how I interact with an individual
goes back into what I've been wrestling
with with regards to the racial
discourse with regards to any sort of
identitarian discourse like how do you
hold onto yourself as a human being and
as a man and as I and then as Benjamin
you know like how do you go through all
those different and contain all those
different categories and not let the
category corrupt the individual but not
to think that the individual is so free
of category that the category doesn't
actually exist anymore yeah there's a
lot of wiggle room but that doesn't mean
that those categories don't have a very
strong foundation and and to deny those
categories and deny the exploration of
those categories is to cut ourselves off
from certain knowledge that will
reproduce itself in
some behavior over and over and over
again because we can't escape that we're
not at the point where we can just
unplug from the body and upload
ourselves into the mind and into the
into the network where we're not at that
point yet so I try to model humility
while it's still having the courage to
take a position you know like you know
and then be wrong and then to allow for
people to show me where I'm wrong and so
that they can have their ideas voiced
yeah thank you thank you for modeling
that with your project and for bringing
all of these things here to us today it
is a really important conversation to be
having and it's so difficult it's really
helpful to have like role models and
some some ideas about what we can do to
actually begin to open up these
questions so I just have a lot of
gratitude for what you're doing thank
you thank you thanks for having me on it
absolutely
well Peter yes like with like a song we
do yes that's after we stop pressing
record and we start singing with you
just just that like the Ravens thoughts
like oh so Ben and I have been belong to
this podcasting mastermind group for a
while now and I've always been really
really impressed with you and just
engaging in these topics and the way you
engage with them so you know just keep
what you're doing what you're doing then
and thanks for coming on
thanks agree I'm seeing and everyone for
the excellent questions next events
tomorrow we got maybe gray who's in the
room maybe do want you want to just do
another shout out to what you we have a
story for you yeah absolutely I think it
actually ties in a lot with the sort of
concepts that we talked about today I'm
gonna be talking about how only fans has
kind of exploded and is all over the
internet um talking about like why
pornography might be a big thing
cheering ovid and what that says about
our relationships to our sexuality
especially like under social distancing
circumstances and I hope I can like chat
a lot in a way that D stigmatizes the
longing that we're still feeling with
for each other and like just celebrate
that we still desire to connect with
each other and and maybe like pull pull
out some of these identitarian issues
that we have was talk
about our experiences of Attraction and
gender and sex and all that kind of
great stuff yeah I love that it's gonna
be a juicy session and then the same day
we have Daniel 'shmock Tim burger sounds
making mensch and that's at 7:00 p.m.
Eastern Time
check out the other of the wisdom Jim
there's more events Daniel Thornton's
welcome back party it's gonna be posted
and that's not gonna be on Monday at
6:30 p.m. Eastern time so that's really
really fun check out the store w dad
know about CA for events center therm
analyst and so is based off a gift
economy I'm reviewing as a gift during
this time of need
if you're inspired to give a gift of the
stoy just check out the gift economy
information alright everyone thank you